Wen-leung.
阿良
Your brother found out about the last shipment.
上次那批货你大哥知道了
How could he know?
知道了，怎么会知道？
You ask him.
你问他
The shipment has been seized.
他老早知道了，货也拿走了
Where is Ah-ga?
阿嘉人呢？
Still at the warehouse.
还在货仓
Does my brother know I'm involved?
我大哥知道我也有份吗？
I don't know. Ask Ah-ga.
这个我不知道 你最好去问阿嘉
Wen-leung,
阿良
...now that your brother knows about it,
事情你大哥既然已经知道了
...we have to go and speak to him.
我们过去谈谈，你看看怎么样？
I must speak to Ag-ha first.
我要先问问阿嘉
What do we do now, boss?
现在怎么办？阿叔
Let's wait for Wen-leung to get things organized.
等阿良把事情搞清楚再说
Do you want to wash your hands?
你是不是要洗手？
Please.
你先洗
Excuse me.
先生
Thanks.
借过，谢谢
What are you doing here?
你怎么会在这里？
Aren't you Ah-tsun?
你不是阿春？
No, you're mistaken.
你认错人了，我不是
Wen-leung, what's going on?
阿良，什么事情？
We've met before, in Chiu-fen.
我们在九份见过面？
Leave me alone. I told you I'm not Ah-tsun.
你这个人怎么这么番？ 我跟你说我不是
Her name is Ah-man.
她叫阿满
Leave us.
进去
Do you have Red Monkey's money?
红猴那笔钱是不是你吞了？
What are you saying? Fool!
你胡说些什么？ 我听不懂，疯子
What's this?
阿良，你在干什么？
Kim-tsua, it's none of your business.
金泉 没你的事
Not my business, eh?
什么没我的事 为什么没我的事？
Leave us.
进去
Ah-ga, tell Wen-leung to come here.
阿嘉，进去叫阿良出来
Ungrateful boy!
你是个不肖子
You came back from overseas.
说起你从海外回来
We gave you the chance to reform.
看看你会不会改过
But did you change? No.
你有改过吗？ 你没有
You are a lowlife,
专门结交乱七八糟的人
...and your friends are lowlifes.
你娘的 只会结交那些不三不四的人
Ah-shue, bring water.
阿雪，水端过来
There's blood on you and in the room. How do you think that'll be taken?
弄得血流血滴，整个人整个厅 这样好看吗？
I know.
你自己想
Look at your father!
要是跟老爸比起来
Did I ever annoy people...
在这个田寮港
...in this district? No.
谁最不满意我
Only the Japanese government.
日本政府最不满意我
They called me a gangster.
说我是流氓
Me a gangster?
我是什么流氓
The Japanese government certainly hated me.
没错，那个时候 日本政府最不满意我
But it was only to help the district.
我也是为了我们这个庄内
I turned big problems into small ones,
大事化小 小事化无
...and got rid of small ones.
我不会拿人家 也不会沾人家的
I never stole anything from anyone,
一草不拿，一草不沾
...and that's why the local gangs supported me.
所以各地方的兄弟都拥护我
But you do nothing honestly.
像你这样，正途的工作你不做 专门做些邪魔歪道的事情
It's always something dishonest.
像你，做兄嫂的
Look at your daughter-in-law.
做大哥的
And at your brother.
你娘的，做什么大哥 兄嫂的义务你们说？
And you, Wen-leung.
他怎么会这样？
Have you fulfilled your obligations?
干你娘
Everything was clear at the beginning.
当时大家都讲得一清二楚
Who'd have known they'd done this.
我怎么知道他们会这样
Didn't you speak to them about it?
你没找他们吗
Of course.
当然有找他们
Let's gather everyone together and clarify the issues.
大家都找出来，事情讲清楚
Ah-chuan,
阿川
...go tell your boss I want to see him.
去找憨丁，说我找他
This is disagreeable!
可恶，乱来
Ah-ga, where are those fellows from Shanghai?
阿嘉，那些上海仔怎么样？
I haven't seen them.
没见到人
Damn it!
干你娘
It's Wen-leung again.
阿良又这样
As if we didn't have enough problems.
事情已经多了
I don't know what to say.
我都不知道怎么讲
Leave me here.
前面这里
How are you?
金泉，好久不见
Where is your boss?
现在在做什么？
He went out.
老大不在
Mrs. Ah-Kio.
阿捡姐
Take a seat please.
大家坐、大家坐
You honor me by coming to see me.
你们今天能够来找我 我很高兴
It gives me hope.
让我阿捡很有面子
There's nothing that can't be repaired.
人说天破都可以补
Everyone knows what times we live in.
现在这个时机 你们也是知道的
You all grew up together.
而且你们从小一起长大
You shouldn't be at odds over this.
有什么好计较的，省省事吧
Our Kim-tsua began this, so he's at fault.
我们金泉先动手，是比较不对
But the whole incident...
不过事情
...began with the return of Red Monkey's Japanese money in Chiu-fen.
是从九份红猴那些日本钱 牵扯出来的
Kim-tsua says...
金泉他说
...that Red Monkey was planning to cheat him,
红猴是想坑他小兄弟的钱
...and so he went to see him.
金泉替他小兄弟去讨钱
Red Monkey didn't want to return the money.
红猴还不吐出来
That's how it all began.
事情才发生的
Kim-tsua had a woman he liked there.
金泉这样说也有道理啊
Maybe Kim-tsua was in the wrong, but...
金泉会跟别人乱来
...he would never lie to me.
对我绝对不会说谎
Red Monkey is dead,
现在红猴人死都死了
...and so can't give his version of the story.
也不能出来金泉对质
This fighting and squabbling must end!
再说打架杀人 就像杀猪公送礼有来有往
Have some tea.
用茶，用荼……
This entire conversation makes no sense.
话说这么多也没有用
The most important thing is to take care of the money.
现在最要紧的 就是这些钱要解决，不解决不行
I think it must be split three ways.
照我的意思分三份
One part for your brother,
你弟弟一份
...one for Kim-tsua...
金泉一份
...and one for Red Monkey's old mother.
红猴他母亲年纪这么大了 一定要给他一份
Yesterday I went to Wen-ching's house,
昨天去文清他家
...and so I didn't write in my diary.
在他家过夜，日记没写
Wen-sun's wife told me things...
晚上跟他二嫂聊天
...about Wen-ching's childhood.
听她说文清小时候的事情
Of the brothers, Wen-sun studied the most,
二嫂说他们兄弟
...but Wen-ching was the most intelligent.
二哥最会读书 不过，文清最聪明
He said his physical problems were due to the gods being jealous.
二嫂说他身体会这样 是老天忌妒
Wen-sun disappeared...
他二哥去南洋当兵
...in the Philippines.
一直没回来
His family don't think he'll return,
文清他们一家人早就看开了
...but his wife cleans...
只有二嫂
...his clinic every day.
每天都把诊所整理得干干净净
Every day she disinfects...
针筒、针头
...the needles and syringes.
每天早上都拿去消毒
She thinks he's still alive...
只有她相信 二哥一定还平平安安的活着
...and that he'll come home one day.
有一天会回来
Then everything will be as it was.
一回来，就跟以前一样
He'll look after his patients,
开始替人看病
...write prescriptions, do injections,
开药、打针
...listen to music... to Beethoven.
听唱片、听贝多芬
Brother.
大哥
Who's down below?
楼下怎么了？
Soldiers from the mainland. Get away.
你快逃 外面很多阿山兵要抓你
What do they want with me?
干你娘，他们抓我什么？
Hurry up and get out.
你先逃再说
What's going on?
什么事？
They have come for Wen-heung.
有人来抓大哥，我们要走了
They have come for us.
走啦
Go back to bed!
你进去里面
This is breaking and entering.
发生什么事？
Search for him.
搜
They told us your son was a collaborator.
有人密报你儿子是汉奸
My son, a collaborator?
我儿子是汉奸？
Somebody denounced him.
有人密报
And that makes him a traitor?
有人密报就是汉奸啊！
We have to take him in for interrogation to find out the truth.
要带去问清楚
Do you eat fish all day?
你他妈的 你们都是吃稀饭的啊？
What kind of mayor are you?
你当什么里长
It's not easy for us.
里长难当啦
Then you'll never find out the truth.
难当就可以好坏不分
Someone denounced him.
有人密报的啦
If that makes you a collaborator,
有人密报就是汉奸啊
...then I'm a gangster.
我是流氓
I went in and out of prison during the Japanese occupation.
日本时代被捉去关了又关
You have to find out the truth.
你们应先查清楚
How does that make him a traitor?
这样叫做汉奸吗？
We'll investigate.
我们会查啦
Investigate? What does that mean?
会查？这是什么意思？
If he's a traitor, then we all are!
像这样就是汉奸 怎么捉得完
We'll make a full investigation.
会查清楚啦
My son and I are gangsters,
我们父子是流氓是没错
...I admit it.
为什么当流氓？
But only for the good of the entire district.
还不是为了维护整个庄子
So as not to be intimidated by the Japanese.
免受日本欺负
If that's being a collaborator,
这样就是汉奸？
...then you are one too.
这样是汉奸 那你也是汉奸
Officer, the man who denounced him is the collaborator.
大人，我向你密报 他也是汉奸
You can't arrest everyone who is denounced.
有人密报就是汉奸 这样汉奸怎么捉得完
Who are you kidding?
骗谁啊？
Wen-leung!
文良！
"Dear uncle:
四叔
...yesterday soldiers arrested Wen-leung.
三叔不知为何 昨天被军人捉去了
They also went to the office to arrest father...
兵也去捉爸爸
...but he escaped, and only injured a leg.
还好爸爸跑得快 只是脚受伤
They say someone denounced Wen-leung...
听说军人会来捉
...and said he was a collaborator.
是有人密报三叔是汉奸
They say he helped the Japanese...
说他当兵的时候在上海
...capture many people in Shanghai.
替日本人做了很多 陷害上海人的事
Even if were true, they must have forced him to do it.
三叔若真如此 也是不得已的不是吗？
Mother says you have friends in Taipei.
阿母说，你台北朋友多
Do you know anyone who might be able to secure his freedom?
能不能找有头脸的人 想办法把三叔保出来
We have money.
钱都准备好了
Please help us and get in touch with us as soon as possible.
拜托四叔千万要尽快联络
Ah-shue".
阿雪
I know.
我知道
Are you looking for Mr. Chen, the town councilor?
你议会陈先生那里有没有去？
It doesn't matter. We need your help.
有什么关系嘛 我们是要拜托人家
Why does it have to be like this?
你为什么要这样说嘛
It's OK. If that's how you think, forget it.
好啦，好啦 你要这样说就算了
I'll prepare it.
我会准备
I know. Someone will deliver it.
我知道 我会叫人拿过去
Mum.
阿母
We have guests.
叔叔带客人来了
I'm coming.
我马上来
They'll free him?
文良放出来了？
Not yet, but I think it will turn out well.
还没有，我想是不要紧
Why haven't they released him?
为什么还没有放出来啦？
Friends in Taipei have made enquiries. Nanking says...
我朋友在台北打听 南京来的消息
...that charges against Taiwanese of collaboration will be withdrawn.
说台湾人不再用 汉奸条例来治罪
So I don't think there'll be any problems.
所以我相信不要紧
But first they have to announce...
但是还没有发布命令前 是不会放出来
...the new regulations.
所以还要等一段时间 不要紧的，大家放心
You must help us!
先生你要多帮忙
Calm down.
冷静一点
Maybe friends in Taipei will be able...
我想找朋友在台北帮忙
...to obtain his release earlier.
看能不能把文良早点放出来
Please, call your brother.
不然这样 麻烦你打个电话给他大哥
He’ll know what to do.
跟他讲比较清楚
Right.
好
Get me Taipei 24.
麻烦你接二十四号
Please, do all you can.
好、那就拜托了
Thanks, thanks.
谢谢、谢谢
And?
怎么样？
They say the law on collaboration is going to be changed.
说什么现在台湾 汉奸检肃条例要改
Damn.
干你娘
They make laws, and they change laws.
反正法律他们设的 随便他们翻起翻落
This island is in a bad way.
我们本岛人最可怜
First the Japanese, then the Chinese.
一下日本人，一下中国人
They all exploit us and no one gives a damn.
众人吃，众人骑 没人疼
Brother.
大哥
Sit down.
来，这边坐
Sit down, please.
坐啦
I am sorry to trouble you...
失礼
...while you are enjoying yourselves.
你们正玩得兴致打扰你们
My brother has been arrested and imprisoned.
我们阿良，现在被抓进牢里
You know people in power.
我知道你们跟机关比较熟
I need your help.
要拜托你们
Can you arrange for him to be set free for New Year?
看能不能过年前打把弄出来
Wen-heung is sorry to bother you,
现在，不好意思打扰你们
...but his brother has been arrested.
阿良现在被捉进去了
He'd like your help so he can be released for New Year.
大哥的意思 希望过年前把他弄出来
They want Wen-leung...
他们是说阿良的事情
...to be released before New Year.
希望能在过年前把他弄出来
When did they arrest him? I knew nothing of this.
阿良什么时候被抓进去了？ 我不知道啊
I didn't know either.
我不知道
They didn't know Wen-leung had been arrested.
阿良被捉，我们都不知道
How can we help?
有什么我们可以帮忙的？
Hypocrites! It's all your fault!
干你娘，事情都是你们搞出来的 还装蒜
Shut up!
你在哭啊
Idiot!
你脑子坏了啊？
Can't you keep your mouth shut?
跟他们讲那么多干什么
Tell them...
告诉他们
...that I know what to do.
礼数我懂
It's all fixed.
东西都准备好了
He says he knows the rules.
我大哥说，礼数他知道
It's all there.
东西在这里
He's back!
美黛
Put him down here.
这边
Wen-leung!
文良！
Bring medicines,
快点，拿伤药来
...a container and a spoon!
碗跟汤匙
Wen-leung,
文良！
...how could they have beat you like that?
怎么被打成这样？
Hurry, fetch a doctor!
去叫客家人医生来
Calm down.
安静，不要哭
Crying won't help.
你哭事情怎么做？
Bring water.
拿水来
Am I talking to the clinic?
惠安诊所
Is the doctor there? Please, hurry up.
医生在吗？拜托，请快点来
Open your mouth.
把他嘴扒开
Why is there so much blood?
怎么流那么多血？
He was OK in the car.
带回来还好好的
The vibrations must have made him lose blood.
在车上一震动血都喷出来了
Damn.
干你娘
Did you call?
电话打了没有？
Yes.
打了
I'll call again.
我再去打
Open your mouth.
再来，把他嘴扒开
Get me the Hui-an Clinic.
帮我接惠安诊所
Tell him it's urgent!
拜托他快一点
I don't know why,
我不知最近怎么了
...but I have had a lot of bad dreams lately.
睡觉常常做梦
They were about dad...
每次都梦到
...tying me to a telegraph pole when I was a boy.
小时候被我爸爸绑在电线杆上
Did you boil the water?
水滚了没有？
Yes.
水滚了
I remember.
我记得有一年
It was just before New Year.
也是过年前
When my father was young, he loved gambling.
我阿爸年轻的时候很爱赌
We had no money and mum...
快过年了，家里没半分钱
...took out a gold necklace...
我阿母拿了一条金项链
...and asked dad to pawn it.
叫我阿爸拿去当
My mother was afraid that dad...
我阿母怕我阿爸
...would gamble away the money and sent me with him.
把当的钱又拿去赌 叫我跟他一起去
As soon as my father had the money in his hand,
结果我阿爸钱刚拿到手
...he persuaded me to stand next to a telegraph pole.
把我骗到电线杆边
He then tied me to it with his belt and went off to bet.
裤带解下来把我绑在电线杆上 自己去赌
It was December and very cold.
十二月天好冷啊
No one went by.
整条路都没人来
It was almost 9 before someone...
快天黑了才有人经过
...saw me and untied me.
看我被绑在那里 才帮我解开
I almost died of the cold.
冻得差点死掉
After that, whenever mum asked me...
以后我阿爸出门要做什么
...to go with dad, I refused.
我阿母叫我跟他一起去 我都不去
Citizens of Taiwan:
台湾同胞
On the night of the 27th, during an investigation in Taipei,
台北市在前一天晚上 二十七日夜里
...unfortunately someone was killed.
因查缉私烟误伤了人命
I have already take the matter...
这件事
...in my own hands.
我已经处置了
The people who killed others during this incident...
缉私烟误伤人命的人
...have already been brought to court to be judged...
我已经交法院严格讯办
....and punished.
处以适当的刑罚
We have ordered medical attention...
一个被打伤的女人
...for a woman with light wounds.
伤势并不重
I have asked for her to be treated
但我已经为她治疗
And I have given her money for the sake of her tranquility.
并且给以安慰的钱
We have to leave for Taipei.
宽美，我待会要赶去台北
Today, the radio spoke of riots in Taipei...
今天收音机说台北发生事情
...between Taiwanese and mainlanders.
台湾人和外省人相杀
Taiwan is under martial law.
台北宣布戒严
In the hospital we are all scared.
医院的人都在说这件事情
One war has just ended.
大家都怕 一个战争才刚结束
Is another about to begin?
另一个战争怎么会接替就来
My brother came to see me.
哥哥来医院找我
He is going to Taipei with Wen-ching.
他和文清要去台北
But this time...
这个时候
...it's very dangerous to go there.
要去那么危险的地方
They have urgent business there.
我知道他们一定有事情要做
I'm very worried but dare not say anything.
心里替他们担心 也不敢说出口
Wen-ching with his disability...
文清他身体不方便
...you have to look after him, brother.
哥你千万要照顾好
Where?
在哪里？
Death to the mainlanders!
杀外省人啊！
Halt, this is a hospital.
住手，这里是医院
Hurry, take him in.
赶快进来
This is a hospital, you can't make a disturbance.
这是医院，不要在这闹事
Get out of here.
拜托，看我的面子
Citizens of Taiwan:
台湾同胞
Yesterday measures were announced...
关于这次事件的处置
...to control disorder,
我昨天已经广播过
...and I hope they were heard and understood.
你们都应该听到 明白我的意思
Now, to restore...
我现在为了安定人心
...calm and order quickly,
迅速恢复秩序
...I am issuing more merciful measures.
作更宽大的措施
They are as follows:
特别再宣布几点处置办法
First, regarding those involved...
一、凡是参加这次事件之人民
...the government will not go ahead...
政府念其由于冲动，缺乏理智
...and punish them.
准予从宽一律不加追究
Second, those arrested...
二、因参与这次事情
...for taking part in the disorder,
已经被宪警拘捕之人员
...will be set free.
准予释放
They'll be taken to police headquarters...
均送宪兵团部
...where their families will be able to come by and look for them.
由其父兄或家族领回
To make things simpler,
不必由邻里长保释
...mayors will issue no guarantees.
以免手续麻烦
Third, the wounded and the dead...
三、此次伤亡的人
...whatever their jobs,
不分公教人员与人民
...whether Taiwanese or mainlanders,
不份本省人与外省人
...will receive medical attention or appropriate compensation.
伤者给以治疗 死者优予抚恤
Fourth, a special committee...
四、这次事件如何善后
...will be set up.
特别设立委员会
It will consist of representatives of the government,
这个委员会除政府人员
...the judicial and municipal authorities.
参政员，参议员等外
It will also include members of the public...
并追加各界人民代表
...with the aim of reflecting true public opinion.
以便可容纳多数人民的意见
What are you doing here?
你怎么在这儿？
And my brother?
哥哥呢？
Doctor! Come quickly!
医生，快来啊
Citizens of Taiwan:
台湾同胞
Yesterday saw the temporary reintroduction of martial law.
昨天我再宣布临时戒严
I want to assure all those of you who love peace,
我此刻以十二万分诚意 告诉最多数的善良百姓
...that this decree is...
我的宣布戒严
...for your protection.
完全是为了保护你们
Take no notice of rumors about spies,
你们千万不要听信奸人的谣言
...because suspicion leads to fear.
有点疑惑，有点恐慌
I assure all citizens...
对于守法的百姓
... who obey the law, that nothing will happen to them.
绝不稍加伤害 你们千万放心
Meanwhile, I am announcing the reintroduction of martial law.
我之所以再宣布戒严
Our objective is merely to punish rebels and traitors.
完全是为了对付 绝少数的乱党叛徒
For every day they are at large,
他们一天不消灭
...peace loving people will have to put up with another day of disorder.
善良的同胞，一天不得安宁
Dead?
被人打死是不是？
Where are you from?
你哪里人？
Where are you going?
要去哪里？
I am... Taiwanese.
台湾人
Are you from Japan?
哪里人？
Must be a mainlander.
这一定是阿山外省人
What are you doing?
你要干什么？
He is deaf.
他是聋子
He can't hear what you are saying.
八岁就听不见了 他跟他说什么他怎么听得见
Wen-ching.
文清
What's the matter, brother?
哥哥，你怎么这样啦？
Is it fractured?
帮我看看骨头有没有断
I don't know.
我不知道啦
Lin has disappeared.
林老师失踪
They've arrested everyone in the special committee.
处理委员会的人都被抓走
The troops of Chen Yi...
陈仪调兵
...are killing and arresting people.
一路捉，一路杀
Your son has come back, ma'am.
老板娘，少爷回来了 回来了
You are back! I was so worried.
你回来了啊！让我担心死了
Soldiers and police came here every day.
家里宪兵、警察天天来
They were right on the doorstep.
门槛都快踩平了
What's wrong with your foot?
你脚是怎么了？
Is it serious?
伤得这么严重？
What are you doing? It's good that he's back!
你怎么了？ 回来就好了，你是在干什么
You can't stay here. I'll hide you in Lai-Liao.
家里不能住 你赶快躲到内寮去
Hinomi,
宽美
...I forbid you to leave the house.
你一步都不准出去
I'll write to the hospital.
院长那边我会写信跟他讲
On 19th March, the director of the hospital,
三月十九日，院长来家里
...took all my things.
把我所有的东西都送回来
It was my father's idea.
这知道这是父亲的意思
There was a letter from Ah-shue.
行李里面有一封阿雪的信
Wen-ching has been arrested.
文清被军人抓走了
They say it was for Mr. Lin.
说是跟林老师有关系
Wen-ching's father went around shouting:
文清他父亲在骂
"They are even arresting the deaf. Where is justice in this world?"
连聋子也抓 这个世间还有没有天理
Justice is not important to me.
天理有无我不管
I only want to know...
现在我只想知道
...where Wen-ching is.
文清他人在哪里
...if he's alive and well.
要是活着就好
Wu Chin-wen, Tai Tung-ho, to court.
吴继文，蔡东和，开庭
Lin Wen-ching, to court!
林文清出庭
Uncle, it's supper time.
阿叔吃饭了
Uncle, you can't eat that.
叔叔这不能吃啦 我跟你讲过几次了
You mustn't!
这不能吃
Wen-leung.
文清先生
Where is Wen-ching?
文清呢？
He went out yesterday and hasn't come back.
我不知道，他昨天就出去了 到现在还没回来
And your father?
你阿爸去哪？
No idea. He went out this morning.
不知道，他早上就出去了